<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rider of the vvhite horse and his army, their late good successe in Yorre-shiere [sic], or, A true and faithfull relation of that famous and wonderfull victory at Bradford, obtained by the club-men there, with all the circumstances thereof. And of the taking of Leeds and Wakefield by the same men under the command of Sir Thomas Fairfax, with the manner and circumstances thereof from good hands. Seriously commended to the high court of Parliament, and all that are of God's side for their incouragement.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1447</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E88_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22370</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871725</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871725</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155713</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91816)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155713)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 15:E88[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rider of the vvhite horse and his army, their late good successe in Yorre-shiere [sic], or, A true and faithfull relation of that famous and wonderfull victory at Bradford, obtained by the club-men there, with all the circumstances thereof. And of the taking of Leeds and Wakefield by the same men under the command of Sir Thomas Fairfax, with the manner and circumstances thereof from good hands. Seriously commended to the high court of Parliament, and all that are of God's side for their incouragement.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 7 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Vnderhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb. 8 1642".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, --  Baron, 1612-1671 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Yorkshire (England) --  History, Military --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Campaigns --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155713:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155713:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RIDER OF THE WHITE HORSE And His ARMY, Their late good Succeſſe in YORRE-SHIERE.</p>
            <p>OR A true and faithfull Relation of that famous and wonderfull victory at <hi>Bradford,</hi> obtained by the Club-men there, with all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances thereof.</p>
            <p>And of the taking of <hi>Leeds</hi> and <hi>Wakefield</hi> by the ſame men under the command of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> with the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and circumſtances thereof from good hands.</p>
            <p>Seriouſly commended to the High Court of PARLIAMENT, and all that are of GODS ſide for their incouragement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderhill,</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155713:2"/>
            <head>BRADFORDS Deliverance.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> his Excellency had retired from <hi>Tadcaſter,</hi> the Lord of <hi>New-caſtle</hi> poſſeſſed himſelfe of <hi>Pontefract,</hi> ſo making himſelfe Maſter of our Weſterne parts, block't up all paſſages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene us and our ſtrength, and then manifeſted his reſolutions to ſeſſe the whole County, but to exact extraordinary ſummes of thoſe who had ſubſcribed the Parliaments Propoſitions. We could expect nothing now, but that thoſe Townes ſhould firſt ſuffer, who had bin moſt forward to aſſiſt the Parliament: <hi>Leeds, Bradford</hi> and <hi>Halifax</hi> were principally aimed at. In <hi>Leeds</hi> the malignant humour being predominant, eaſily converted the Towne into their temper. <hi>Bradford</hi> was the next place in their way, the Towne moſt unable to reſiſt them; and indeed who ever conſiders their dangers, weakneſſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, muſt judge their attempt as worthy admiration as their ſucceſſe. The maine body of the Popiſh Army was within a dayes march of <hi>Bradford,</hi> ſome amongſt them grievouſly exaſperated by a diſhonourable repulſe from this Towne not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. So farre were we from expecting help from the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> as we thought it ſcarce poſſible to ſeeke it: Our malignant ſpirits before charmed, now appeared, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing forth nothing but threatnings againſt thoſe who had bin moſt active for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: and their apparition was ſo terrible, as it affrighted many of the beſt affected perſons out of the Towne; and thereupon, out goes our Royaliſts to bring in the Kings Catholick Army. Some religious perſons in the Pariſh, conſidering what danger might reſult both to their conſciences and Country from ſuch cowardize and treachery (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigated by feare of perjury, if they ſhould contribute any aſſiſtance againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and care of their lives and Eſtates, evidently endangered by a bare refuſall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſiſtance) reſolved to ſtand upon then guard, invited all the well affected in the Pariſh to aſſiſt them, and entred the Towne. When our Malignants were returned with a Letter from Sir <hi>William Savile,</hi> wherein he manifeſted an intention to burne and plunder, if we did not contribute to the maintenance of the Popiſh Army. To which no other anſwer was return'd, then the apprehenſion of thoſe who brought it, and had ſubſcribed it; All couragious attempts, yea deſperate in the account of many, who ſaw neither wiſedome nor ſtrength ſufficient to manage them; There wanted both the head, body and ſinewes of warre, we had never a Gentleman in the Pariſh to command us, nor would any ſtranger be perſwaded to undertake the charge. All our trained Souldiers with their Armes, were with the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and the moſt of thoſe who were fitted for ſervice as voluntiers. Nor could it be expected, that the well affected
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155713:2"/>of our poore Pariſh, could pay a Garriſon any long time, and none would carry one day without pay. Our neighbours perceived this, and therefore judging our attempt deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate (as in the eye of reaſon it was) and fearing the iſſue would be our ruine, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to helpe us, leaſt they ſhould periſh with us. Nor wanted we diſcouragements from our own men, to inſtance in no more; the very night before the Enemy aſſaulted us, the greateſt part of them left us. This was on Saturday, <hi>Decemb:</hi> 17. The next morning about 9 of the Clock the Enemy was diſcovered, approaching the Eaſt end of the Towne: They were marſhald in two Bodies, the Van was commanded by Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Evers</hi> (eldeſt Sonne to the Lord <hi>Evers</hi>) wherein were 3 Troopes of Horſe, 2 Companies of Dragooners, 100 Foot, 20 Pyoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, 2 Drakes, the traine of Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, commanded by Major <hi>Carew</hi> a Dutch man. The Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was commanded by Sir <hi>Francis Howard,</hi> wherein were his own and Captaine <hi>Hiliards</hi> Troops, 6 Companies of Collonel <hi>Eddringtons</hi> Dragooners, and a 100 Foote. Collonel <hi>Goring</hi> came along with them, and ſome ſay the Earle of <hi>Newport;</hi> but whether they had any charge or no in this expedition I heare not. All theſe our <hi>York-ſhiere</hi> Gentlemen had procured of the Lord of <hi>New caſtle,</hi> as though Sir <hi>William Savils</hi> Regiment, Sir <hi>Marmaduke Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Gleman</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Gothericks</hi> Troopes, Sir <hi>Ingram Hopton,</hi> Captain <hi>Nevill,</hi> Captaine <hi>Batt.</hi> Captaine <hi>Bins</hi> Companies had not bin ſufficient to have ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed our deſpicable Towne: I ſhould now ſhew how our men were marſhald, but 'tis a hard matter to marſhall thoſe who had neither Commanders, Collours, nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Companies. The night before, we had borrowed a Commander of <hi>Hallifax,</hi> wee had neere upon 40 Musquets and Calievers, in Towne about 30 Fowling, Birding and ſmaller Peeces, and well nigh twice as many Club men. Theſe our Captaine diſpoſed in ſeverall parts of the Towne, 10 or 12 of your beſt marks men upon the Steeple, and ſome in the Church; Who being next the Enemy, awaited not their warning peece, but at the firſt fight gave fire upon them bravely. The Enemy who expected a ſurrender, rather then reſiſtance, being herewith ſomething daunted; and perceiving how advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious the Steeple was to us, preſently poſſeſt themſelves of ſome Houſes not farre from the Church, very convenient for the ſhelter of their men, and planting of their Ordnance, and from thence ſent out Sir <hi>Iohn Gothericks</hi> Troope, who partly to divert us from hindring them planting their Canon, and partly to hinder the Pariſh from comming in to our aid, paſt through ſome Pariſh villages on the one ſide of the Towne, robbed a Woman, moſt cowardly ſlew two naked Men, and ſo came within fight of our Sentinell at the Weſt end of the Towne, Our Muſquetiers there diſcharged at them, ſhot 2 or 3 Horſes, whereof one of them lightly wounded was brought into Towne; and in a ſhort ſpace (partly by our ſhot, partly by the approach of ſome Club-men from <hi>Bingley</hi>) they were forced to retire back to their ſtrength. In the meane time their Canons were planted in places moſt convenient for battering the Steeple, (which did moſt annoy them) and ſcowring of <hi>Kirkgate,</hi> downe which, our men muſt upon ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity march to reſiſt them; This done, Major <hi>Carew</hi> draws down ſome Foot, and therewith takes two Houſes within 30 yards of the Church, and this he did without any other impeachment then from the Steeple; Wee having not any ſtrength to ſally out upon them, from theſe Houſes they plaid upon the Church very hotly, and the Church upon them: Our Steeple had a notable advantage of them, which our Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitiers there eſpecially improved againſt them, for when any Buffe or skarlet Coat ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, they laid 2 or 3 of their Peeces in one hole, and diſcharged at once upon them with good ſucceſſe, and thereby deterred the reſt from relieving their men in the Houſes,
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:155713:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:155713:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:155713:4"/>and thus they continued till high-noone, about which time there came to our aid from <hi>Hallifax</hi> ſome Fire-men and many Clubbs, ſuch of theſe as came to fight, were forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with drawne downe to ſervice, ſome of them were placed in the Church, others in Lanes neare the fore-ſaid Houſes; The Church and Lanes kept the Houſes in play, and the Steeple hindred the Enemy from relieving the Houſes. But this was not the way to repell the Enemy. The largeneſſe of the Church windowes, and ſmalneſſe of the Houſes, made their aſſault ſecure, and our defence dangerous, which our men perceiving, reſolved to win or loſe all at once; watching an opportunity betwixt the diſcharge and charge of the Enemy, they ſallyed out of the Church, and being ſeconded by thoſe in the Lanes, ruſhed in upon the Houſes, burſt open the doores, ſlew thoſe that reſiſted, tooke thoſe who yeelded; the reſt fled into the next Field, whither ſome few of ours followed, (the greateſt part being employed in conveying the Men and Munition which the Enemy had left behind them) and in the Field the skirmiſh was hotter then ever; Our men were too eager to keepe Ranke or File, though they had knowne how to keepe it, and indeed their diſorder was an advantage to us, for mixing themſelves with the Enemy, they fought ſecurely in the mouth of the Enemies Canon, and in the eye of one Body of their Forces, both placed in the Field above them; the Enemy not daring to diſcharge, leaſt with them they ſhould ſlay their own Men, (otherwiſe, they having 10 Fire-men for one, might have cut us off in an inſtant) nor could ours uſe their Muskets otherwiſe then as Clubbs. To ſpeake ingeniouſly, their Commanders exaſperated by the cowardize of their common Souldiers, manifeſted great courage, but they ſmarted for it; our Sythes and Clubbs now and then reaching them, and none elſe did they aime at: One amongſt the reſt in a Scarlet Coate, our Club-men had got hold of (and he in all probability, as ſome credible reports give us occaſion to beleeve, was Collonel <hi>Goring</hi>) and were ſpoiling him. Their Horſe fearing the loſſe of ſuch a Man, became more couragious then they intended, leaped over the hedge, and rode full upon our Men, forcing them to give a little ground; too Much (alas that they had known him) to loſe ſuch a Man, but they quickly recovered the ground 'tho they loſt the Man; doubled their courage, would neither give nor take quarter; (nor was this their cruelty, as the Enemy complaines, but their ignorance) and in the end forced both Man and Horſe to leave the Field; and yet could not we keepe it, for we being ſeparated from theirs, the Musketiers had liberty to play upon us; and indeed they rained ſuch a ſhower of lead amongſt our men, as forced them to retreat for ſhelter to the next hedge, and ſo hindred them from purſuing, till they had removed their Canons. Their Ordnance all this time played upon us, one of them ranged an 8 pound Bullet; yet ſee the Lords mercy to us: that which was planted againſt the Steeple never hit it; another intended for the skouring of <hi>Kirhgate,</hi> 'tho planted in as advantagious a place as they deſired, 'tho the Street was continually crowded with people; yea, though many of their Bullets hit the Houſes, and ſome the Street, yet was no body at all hurt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; they bored indeed 3 or 4 Houſes, yet (which is obſervable) did moſt harme to a Malignants; and thus the terror of the Lord, and of us falling upon them, ſending their Foot and Artilery formoſt, away they went. (uſing their feet better then they uſed their hands) and about 50 of our Clubbs and Muskets after them; Which cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in ours, did moſt of all aſtoniſh the Enemy; who ſay, no 50 Men in the world, except they were madd or drunke, would have purſued a Thouſand: Our men indeed, ſhot as they were madd, and the Enemy fell as they were drunke, and ſo we will devide it. Some diſcharged 10 ſome 12 times in the purſuit; and having the whole Body
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155713:4"/>of the Enemy for their butt, it may eaſily be imagined what good execution they did in a miles march (for ſo farre they purſued them) even to the Moore, where fearing to be environed by their Horſe, they retired, ſome of them ſo wearied with this 8 houres hot ſervice, as they could ſcarce returne to the Towne, One thing I cannot omit, a hearty Round-head left by his comrades, environed with the Enemies Horſe, diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Musket upon one, ſtrooke downe anothers Horſe with the thick end of it, broke a thirds Sword, beating it backe to his throat, and put them all to flight; which (though as the reſt wonderfull) I dare pawne my credit to be true. And thus ended our skirmiſh; wherein there was</p>
            <p>Slaine of theirs, Sir <hi>Iohn Harper,</hi> (as one <hi>Savile</hi> taken at <hi>Halifax</hi> confeſſeth,) Captaine <hi>Wray</hi> (in whoſe pocket was found good ſtore of gold, and a Commiſſion directed to Major <hi>Williams,</hi> which made us thinke him to be the Man) and Captaine <hi>Bins</hi> (whom they carried to <hi>Leeds</hi> ſcarce dead, and buried two daies after) and many common Souldiers, more I am perſwaded then we ſhall ever know of, Of ours, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heare of two that periſhed by the Enemy in the fight.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohn Gothericke</hi> got a baſtinado, had his Horſe killed with a Syth, and about a 100 common Souldiers were wounded, as we are informed from <hi>Leeds</hi> where they are Billeted: Of ours, about 12. all curable except one or two.</p>
            <p>Taken of theirs, Serjant Major <hi>Carew,</hi> (a Man of great account, borne in the Low-Countries of Engliſh Parents) 26 Common Souldiers, about 10 Horſes, 180 weight of Pouder, and about 40 Muskets; and thus God ſupplied our wants out of the ſtore, giving us as many more Muskets as we had, and well-nigh as much Pouder as we ſpent.</p>
            <p>This was the iſſue of the fight, wherein nothing can be ſeene but God, and the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull effects of his glorious Attributes: Let us and our Enemies both ſee it, that they may feare and ſhame, that we may truſt and praiſe our God, who hath manifeſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be the Lord of Hoſts.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:155713:5"/>
            <head>A true Relation of the paſſages at <hi>Leeds,</hi> on Munday the 23. of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> 1642.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> ſon to the Lord Generall <hi>Fairfax,</hi> marched from <hi>Bradford</hi> (ſix miles diſtant from <hi>Leeds</hi>) on Munday morning with 6. Troopes of Horſe, and 3. Companies of Dragoones under the command of Sir <hi>Henry Fowles</hi> Knight, his Lieutenant Generall of the horſe, and neare a 1000 musketeers, with 2000. Club-men, under the command of Sir <hi>William Fairfax</hi> Colonell, and Lieutenant Generall of the Foot. One company of theſe being Dragoones under Capt. <hi>Mildmay,</hi> and about 30 musketiers and 1000 club-men, marched on the South-ſide of the River of <hi>Ayr</hi> to <hi>Hunſlet-more</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove halfe a mile from <hi>Leeds,</hi> on the South-eaſt ſide towards <hi>Wakefield:</hi> and the reſt on the North-ſide Ayr by <hi>Aperley</hi>-bridge (20. yards of <hi>Chriſtall</hi>-bridge being broke downe by the enemy) to <hi>Wood houſe-more.</hi> On the weſt-ſide <hi>Leeds</hi> about a mile thence; where they commending the cauſe to God by prayer, Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> diſpeeded a Trumpeter to Sir <hi>William Savile,</hi> who commanded in chiefe in <hi>Leeds,</hi> requiring in writing that Towne to be delivered him for the King and Parliament; which Sir <hi>William</hi> diſdainfully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and ſaid, he uſed not to give anſwer to ſuch frivolous tickets, being confident (it ſeems) that with the ſtrength he had he could keepe the Towne, wherein were about 2000. men. <hi>viz.</hi> 1500. foot, and 5. Troops of Horſe and Dragoons and two Demicul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verins.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> approached nearer the South-weſt-ſide of the Towne with his Forts that came on the North-ſide ayre, and coming within view of the Towne with banners diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played (about 36. Colours) ſent another Trumpetter to Sir <hi>William,</hi> who ſhortly after by a Trumpetter aſſured him he ſhould get nothing but by fight, whereupon he drew out of his companies 5. Colours of his experteſt Souldiers, and appointed them to march downe with Serjeant Major <hi>Forbes,</hi> Captaines <hi>Briggs, Lee, Francke</hi> and <hi>Palmer,</hi> with his Dragoones on foot, towards the water along the trenches, drawn two yards breadth and height from M. <hi>Harriſons</hi> new Church along the South-ſide of the Towne to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, an inner trench being devided and drawne on the in-ſide that long trench neare the water-ſide, compaſſed about the declivity of the Hill a little above the water. Neare to and above which about a 100 musketiers were drawn out of the Towne, and about 2 of the clock in the after-noone, gave fire from the in-ſide of the works upon Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his musketiers, who approaching nearer ſhrowded themſelves under a hill at the South head of the great fields before the great long Trench, and let fly at the ſaid Centry with no loſſe at all to either ſide, they within the Trenches ſhooting too high, and the other at
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155713:5"/>the Trenches; meane while Sir <hi>W<hi rend="sup">m</hi>. Fairfax,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho Norcliffe,</hi> and other Captains lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their Companies to the Weſt-ſide of the new Church, and the Troopes of Horſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the enemies out-roads in the lanes and fields on the weſt, and north parts; and the forts of the ſouth-ſide ayre, approaching the Bridge, forced the Guarders to quit the works at the firſt centry, placed on the out-ſide the Houſes towards <hi>Beiſton,</hi> brake through the works, and ſhot at the other ſtrong centry at the Bridge end, where the Forts diſcharged upon them without any loſſe to either ſide, but ſeeing the very neare approach of the Dragoons, Musketiers and many Club men and fearing the ſpeedy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing that place they inſtantly fetcht to the bridge the Demiculverin. And after about an hours time ſpent in vain ſhooting between the Forts within and without the works on the ſouth ſide of the Town, as aforeſaid. Serjeant Major <hi>Forbes</hi> moſt bravely leading on his companies in the plain fields before the great Trenches, his Lieutenant <hi>Horsfall</hi> of <hi>Halyfax,</hi> Captaines <hi>Lee, Brigg</hi> and <hi>Francke</hi> contended which ſhould next follow, and Captain <hi>Chadwicks Lancaſhiere</hi> ſouldiers accompanied: Th'enemy ſhot moſt vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Trenches, yet kil'd none.</p>
            <p>It vvas perceived by the Forts on the South-ſide Ayre, that if they could get ſome muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketiers over the fields to the water ſide without danger by the Cannon, and musket from the bridge, they could force the great Centries from their vvorks on the other ſide the river (in regard they had made no other defence againſt the ſouth-ſide vvater) and ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen an eaſie paſſage to Ser-Major <hi>Forbs</hi> &amp; his forces; vvherupon by ſingle perſons they got to the vvater-ſide, and hid them in a little lane (<hi>Iames Nayler</hi> one of the Dragooners be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt) vvhither they had no ſooner got, then the Demiculverin from the bridge plaid neare them, and about 4. muskets from that little lane, and 2. from under a ſtump of a tree, a little above by the vvater-ſide, diſcharged amongſt the Centry, and one man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there ſlain, the reſt perceived their errour, and in concluſion fled apace out of the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Centry, vvhich being eſpied by thoſe on the ſouth-ſide ayre (Serjeant Major <hi>Forbes</hi> and his company not diſcerning them, for the height of their vvorks hindred) a great ſhout from thoſe on the ſouth-ſide of the vvater, diſcovered it to the Serjeant Major, who with his forces comming downe towards the vvater-ſide vvas holpen by Lieutenant <hi>Horsfall,</hi> vvho lending him his ſhoulder to climbe the top of the vvorks, be moſt furviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and boldly entred the works ſingle, him his ſaid Lieutenant (vvading through the river-ſide below the vvorke) next followed moſt reſolutely, them the reſt followed, and M. <hi>Ionathan Scholefield</hi> (the Miniſter at <hi>Croſton</hi> chappell in <hi>Halifax</hi> Pariſh neare <hi>To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>merdeu</hi>) in their Company begun, and they ſung the 1 verſe of the 68 Pſalm, <hi>Let G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>darife, and then his enemies ſhall be ſcattered, and thoſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him flee before him.</hi> And inſtantly after the great ſhout on the ſouth-ſide river, ſtill informing of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies flight from the upper and next Centry (vvhere about a 100 vvere) Serjeant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor entred that alſo, and M. <hi>Scholefield</hi> begun, and they ſung another like verſe. So theſe vvorks being gained, the enemy fled into the Houſes, and ſhot again furiouſly at thoſe vvho had entred their vvorks, vvho purſuing their victory, vvent up along the in-ſide the vvorks to the third centry at the lane neare M. <hi>Metcalſes</hi> houſe, vvhere fierce ſhot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made from a new houſe and all about, two men of Serjeant Major <hi>Forbes</hi> company vvere ſhot dead, here Captain <hi>Lee</hi> entring that centry from the lane, leading from <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall</hi>-bridge, vvas ſhot in the leg above the ankle, ſome bones being broken and took out, he is likely ſhortly to recover. The victory they purſued, though vvith great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty; Captain <hi>Briggs</hi> drawing towards the old-church, vvas from an Houſe ſhot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the chin neare the throat, and in the arme, though not mortally, as is hoped. The
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155713:6"/>Enemy flying along a ſtreet or lane, from the 2. centries neare the vvater into the heart of the Towne, vvhere the other Demiculverin lay to guard that paſſage, Sir <hi>William</hi> met them, and enquiring the cauſe of their flight, vvas anſwered that their vvorkes vvere entred, he called on them, go beat them out, promiſing to lead them, yet they deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: vvhich he ſeeing, and that 12. musketiers, drawne on both ſides that lane by Mr. <hi>Scholefield</hi> had gained that Cannon by killing the Cannoneere (though vvith loſſe of a gray cotes, the one vvherof being ſhot, did fight beyond the ſtrength of a man) he and the reſt, perceiving the Towne loſt, about an houre after the firſt centry vvas ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) fled away, thinking to get over the bridge towards <hi>Wakefield,</hi> and ſome of them (upon occaſion of the club-mens beating backe from that centry by ſhot from any houſe neare the bridge end) got, to the number of 40, by the ſouth-ſide vvater, downe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Hunſlet,</hi> but vvere many of them taken, amongſt vvhom Captain <hi>Thirlwell</hi> Sir <hi>William</hi> ſeeing that vvay blockt, vvith many others fled amain back to the old-Church, by the ſouth-ſide vvhereof by fine force they made way through clubs and fouling peeces along the north-ſide ayre towards <hi>Pomfret.</hi> Sir <hi>William</hi> being neare drowning in the paſſages. Many Antients, Drums and foot taken, and ſome ſlain here, <hi>viz.</hi> Captain <hi>Widrington, Maud</hi> of <hi>Wake-field, Hunſworth</hi> of <hi>Leeds,</hi> and others, captain <hi>Errington</hi> vvas drowned, ſo vvere M. <hi>Robinſon</hi> vicar of <hi>Leeds</hi> and others, <hi>viz</hi> M. <hi>Calvery</hi> of <hi>Calvery,</hi> and M. <hi>Iackſon</hi> of <hi>Leeds;</hi> and 460. common ſouldiers taken, vvith about 14. barrels of Gun-pouder, great ſtore of match, 2 cannons and many muskets. So the Towne being taken about 4 a clook, notice hereof came to <hi>Wakefield</hi> about 6, the Garriſon there about 12 quitted that place, and the Malignants thereof, M <hi>Nevile, Paulden, Reyſer</hi> and the reſt conveyed vvhat goods they could to <hi>Pomfret,</hi> vvhence alſo the next night they fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with 30. carriages, and all except about 200. vvho keepe the caſtle; and captains <hi>Birkehead</hi> and <hi>Wilſon</hi> vvith about 200 muskets and neare 1400. club-men from about <hi>Almurbury,</hi> and 3 Troops from <hi>Leeds,</hi> entred vacant <hi>Wakefield</hi> the ſame Tueſday, and that night, and captaine <hi>Radcliffe,</hi> and neare as many musketiers and club-men on the next day from <hi>Quick,</hi> &amp;c</p>
            <p>As the musketiers and club men retreated from the vvater-ſide after the firſt a centries vvere vvon, the cannon from the bridge played amongſt them, and as they vvent on in the lane, leading to <hi>Beiſton,</hi> it beat downe the barrs of a tenter vvhich flew amongſt them; and the next ſhot from it cruſht the top of an houſe, yet did no more harme; Theſe of <hi>Halifax</hi> Pariſh, <hi>viz.</hi> one <hi>Michael Woodhead</hi> was ſhot upon his tin-buttons, and his dublet burſt neare his heart, and the bruiſed bullet fell downe into his breeches and no more hurt; <hi>Iohn Milnes</hi> man, had his coat, dublet, and 2 ſhirts ſhot through to his coller bone on his back, whence the bullet rebounded and no hurt, but a little rotting of the fleſh ſince; one <hi>Lilly,</hi> M. <hi>Tho. Liſters</hi> man, had a bullet ſhot into the hilt of his ſword, wherby the hilt was drawn out almoſt as ſmall as wyre where the bullet light and no hurt.</p>
            <p>About 20 ſlain, 10. of Sir <hi>Tho: Fairfax</hi> part, wherof Sir <hi>Tho Norcliffe</hi> loſt 2 men, as they entred <hi>Leeds</hi> neare new-church: The works coſt about 500 lb The 460. priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are all diſcharged (ſave about 20) upon oath taken never to ſerve againſt King and Parliament; and <hi>Leeds</hi> and <hi>Wakefield</hi> ſtrongly guarded.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
